A Guide to the University of Virginia School of Medicine Student Notebook Collection, 1836-1943
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
- Student notebook: Biology B, Botany, Volume I 1916 September 25-1917 May 16, ADS notebook with drawings, some in color, also bound with copied lecture notes. (Box-folder 005-002)
  Professors: Ivey Forman Lewis (Miller Professor of Biology and Agriculture) William Allison Kepner (Associate Professor of Biology)
  Class: C. B. Morton took this class when he was an undergraduate student.
- Student notebook: Histology, Embryology, Pathology 1918-1920, ADS notebook (Box-folder 005-003)
  The notes were taken by Charles Bruce Morton. See Box-folder 005-002 for additional information about Morton.
  Professor: Harvey Ernest Jordan (Professor of Histology and Embryology).
- Student notebook: Lab Manual - Histology 1918-1919, notebook with A notes (Box-folder 005-004)
  Professor: Harvey Ernest Jordan (Professor of Histology and Embryology)
  Textbook: Lab. Manual - Histology.
- Student notebook: Surgery and Urology 1920 September 20-1921 March 25, ADS notebook with drawings (Box-folder 005-005)
  Professors: Stephen Hurt Watts (Professor of Surgery and Gynecology) and John Henry Neff (Associate Professor of Genito-Urinary Surgery).
- Student notebook: Surgery, Volume VI 1920 Septmeber 22-1921 May 16, ADS notebook (Box-folder 005-006)
  Professor: William Hall Goodwin (Associate Professor of Surgery and Gynecology).
- Student notebook: Histology 1923 September 19 - 1924 May 29, ADS notebook with drawings, some in color (Box-folder 006-001)
  The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. According to the "University of Virginia Record," Albert Brown Dickey graduated with his MD degree June 1927. Dickey was from Louisiana and was a Medical Director and Superintendent of the State Tuberculosis Hospital in Madisonville, Kentucky. He also served on the consultant staff of Hopkins County Hospital in Madisonville.
- Student notebook: Chemistry 1924 January-May 12, ADS notebook (Box-folder 006-002)
  The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. See Box-folder 006-001 for more information about Dickey.
  Professors: Theodore Hough (Professor of Physiology and Biochemistry), John Seward Lawrence (Associate Professor of Biochemistry), and Bert Barnet Hershenson (Instructor of Physiology and Biochemistry).
- Student notebook: [General Medical Studies, I] Eye, Ear, Nose 1926 September 21 - 1927 March, ADS notebook with drawings (Box-folder 006-003)
  Professors: Unknown.
- Student notebook: [General Medical Studies, II] Nervous Diseases and Legal Medicine 1926 September 21-1927 May 3, ADS notebook (Box-folder 006-004)
- Student notebook: [General Medical Studies, III] [1926] October 5 - [1927] May 21, ADS notebook (Box-folder 006-005)
- Student notebook: Physical Diagnosis, Physiology, Pathology [1924] January 12 - [1925] June 2, ADS notebook (Box-folder 007-001)
  Professors: James Carroll Flippin (Professor of Clinical Medicine), Henry Bearden Mulholland (Instructor of Medicine), and James Edwin Wood (Instructor of Medicine).
- Student notebook: Materia Medica and Pharmacology [1922] september 22 - [1925] June 3, ADS notebook (Box-folder 007-002)
  Professor: James Alexander Waddell (Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica, and Toxicology).
- Student notebook: Physiology [1924] September 24 - [1925] April 17, ADS notebook with drawings (Box-folder 007-003)
  Professors: Theodore Hough (Professor of Physiology and Biochemistry), Bert Barnet Hershenson (Assistant Professor of Physiology and Biochemistry), and Robert Battaille Hiden (Instructor of Physiology and Biochemistry).
- Student notebook: Gynecology and Surgical Pathology [1925] April 19 - [1926] March 9, ADS notebook (Box-folder 007-004)
  Professor: Leroy Adelbert Calkins (Professor of Obstetrics and Genecology).
- Student notebook: Obstetrics [1925] September 21 - [1926] April 1, ADS notebook, 1 TD reprint, 1 booklet (Box-folder 007-005)
  The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. See Box-folder 006-001 for more information about Dickey. Slipped in the notebook is a 1927 booklet entitled "Physicians' Pocket Reference to the International List of Causes of Death," as well as a 1954 reprint from Current Researches in Anesthesia & Analgesia.
- Student notebook: Urology and Orthopedics [1925] September 21 - [1926] May 25, ADS notebook (Box-folder 008-001)
  Professors: Allen Fiske Voshell (Assistant Professor of Orthopedic Surgery) and John Henry Neff (Professor of Genito-Urinary Surgery).
- Student notebook: Surgery [1925] September 23 - [1926] May 18, ADS notebook with drawings (Box-folder 008-002)
  Professors: Stephen Hurt Watts (Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), William Hall Goodwin (Associate Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), Isaac Alexander Bigger (Assistant Professor of Surgery), Frank Helvestine (Instructor of Surgery), John Henry Neff (Professor of Genito-Urinary Surgery), and Dr. Page.
- Student notebook: Pediatrics [1925] September 24 - [1926] March 7, ADS notebook (Box-folder 008-003)
  Professors: Lawrence Thomas Royster (Professor of Pediatrics) and James Alexander Waddell (Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica and Toxicology).
- Student notebook: Internal Medicine [I] and Physiology quiz [1925] September 21 - [1926] May 28, ADS notebook, ADS, TD with AN (Box-folder 008-004)
  The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. See Box-folder 006-001 for more information about Dickey. Included in the book is a 7 page physiology quiz as well as a Secretary's Guide for Phi Chi.
  Professor: James Carroll Flippin (Professor of Clinical Medicine).
- Student notebook: Internal Medicine [II] [1926] September 27 - [1927] April 4, ADS notebook with drawings (Box-folder 008-005)
- Student notebook: Clinical Diagnosis [1926] September 26 - [1927] May 27, ADS notebook (Box-folder 009-001)
  Professor: William Edward Bray (Associate Professor of Clinical Diagnosis and Director of Clinical Laboratories).
- Student notebook: Etiology of Heart Disease N.D., ADS notebook, 1 AN (Box-folder 009-002)
- Student notebook: Orthopedics 1925 February 6-May 8, AD notebook with drawings (Box-folder 009-003)
  The notes were taken by Daniel O. Nichols from Hinton, West Virginia. The notebook is a gift from Dr. Weaver in Culpeper, Virginia dated April 17, 1975. According to the "University of Virginia Record," Daniel Oscar Nichols graduated with his MD degree June 1926. After graduating from medical school, Dr. Daniel Oscar Nichols interned at Blue Ridge Sanatorium and the University of Virginia Hospital while also maintaining his practice in Charlottesville. He became a member of the Virginia Academy of General Practice in 1953.
  Professor: Allen Fiske Voshell (Assistant Professor of Orthopedic Surgery).
- Notebook: Pathology notes 1930 June 24-August 7, ADS notebook (Box-folder 009-004)
  The notebook were taken by Oscar Swineford. This is not be a "student" notebook as Swineford graduated from UVa SOM in 1926. The notebook was written when he was teaching as Instructor in Clinical Pathology, 1928-1930. After receiving the B.S. degree in 1923 and the M.D. degree in 1926 at the University of Virginia, Dr. Swineford joined the faculty of the University of Virginia School of Medicine. He became Professor of Internal Medicine and Head of the Allergy Division at the University of Virginia School of Medicine. Hi was important in encouraging medical schools all over the United States to develop the teaching of allergy. He was President of the American Academy of Allergy and the Southeastern Allergy Association. He was Chairman of the Allergy Section of the Southern Medical Association. He was a member of the Scientific and Educational Council of the Allergy Foundation of America, of the American Rheumatism Association, the Medical Society of Virginia, the American Medical Association, and a fellow of the American College of Physicians. Chiarri is written on the front of the notebook and on pages inside but it is not clear if this is a student or instructor name.
  Donor: Mrs. Blair, daughter of Dr. Swineford, Jr.
- Student notebook: Pathology notes 1930 June 10-August 14, ADS notebook (Box-folder 009-005)
  The notebook were taken by Oscar Swineford. This is not be a "student" notebook as Swineford graduated from UVa SOM in 1926. For additional information about Swineford see Box-folder 009-004. The notebook was written when he was teaching as Instructor in Clinical Pathology, 1928-1930.
- Student notebook: Materia Medica notes 1929-30, ADS notebook (Box-folder 010-001)
  The notes were taken by D. F. Weaver. According to the the "University of Virginia Record," Delmar Franklin Weaver from Orange, Virginia, graduated with an MD degree on June, 14, 1932. After serving as Instructor of Surgery at the University of Virginia School of Medicine, Weaver did a Fellowship at the Rochester, Minnesota, Mayo Clinic in otolaryngology, bronschoscopy and plastic surgery from 1936 to 1939. Later he was associate surgeon in Otolaryngology at Henry Ford Hospital, Detroit. From 1950 to 1970, Weaver was in private practice in Detroit. He was appointed Clinical Professor of Otolaryngology, College of Medicine, Wayne State University in 1963. From 1970 until he retired Weaver was on the staff at Culpeper Memorial Hospital and was a visiting staff member at the UVa Medical Center.
  Professor: James Alexander Waddell (Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica and Toxicology).
- Student notebook: Obstetrics notes 1930 September 22 - 1931 March 10, ADS notebook (Box-folder 010-002)
  The notes were taken by D. F. Weaver. For additional information about Weaver see Box-folder 010-001.
  Professor: Francis Bayard Carter (Associate Professor of Obstetrics).
- Student notebook: Pediatric lecture notes 1930 September 23 - 1931 March 14, ADS notebook (Box-folder 010-003)
  Professors: Lawrence Thomas Royster (Professor of Pediatrics) and William Wirt Waddell, Jr. (Assistant Professor of Pediatrics).
- Student notebook: Surgery lecture notes 1930 September 24 - 1931 May 30, ADS notebook (Box-folder 010-004)
  Professors: Edwin Partridge Lehman (Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), William Hall Goodwin (Professor of Clinical Surgery and Gynecology), Richard Hardaway Meade (Assistant Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), Charles Bruce Morton (Assistant Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), and Caleb Smith Stone (Instructor of Surgery).
- Student notebook: Orthopedics Lecture notes 1931 January 7-May 14, ADS notebook (Box-folder 010-005)
  The notes were taken by D. F. Weaver. For additional information about Weaver see Box-folder 010-001
  The lecturer was Dr. [Allen F.] Voshell.
- Student notebook: Pediatrics 1931 September 21-December 5, ADS notebook (Box-folder 010-006)
  The notes were taken by J. A. M. Thompson. According to the the "University of Virginia Record," John A. Moorman Thompson from Stevensburg, Virginia, graduated with an MD degree on June, 13, 1933. He was on the staff of Blue Ridge Sanatorium, and also served on the staff of the Veterans Hospital at Oteen, N.C.
  Professors: Lawrence Thomas Royster (Professor of Pediatrics) and William Wirt Waddell, Jr. (Assistant Professor of Pediatrics)
  Donors: Ms. Roberta Senechal and Mr. James Skalnik.
- Student notebook: Syphilology 1932 January 5 - 1933 March 17, ADS notebook (Box-folder 010-007)
  The notes were taken by J. A. M. Thompson. For more information on Thompson see Box-folder 010-006.
  Professor: Dudley Crofford Smith (Professor of Dermatology and Syphilology.) Also includes notes in public health taught by Dr. Kenneth F. Maxcy.
- Student notebook: Calibration of Volumetric Apparatus 1937 August 3-September 28, ADS notebook (Box-folder 011-001)
  The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker when he was an undergraduate student. According to the "University of Virginia Record," Armistead Page Booker from New Castle, Delaware, graduated with an MD degree on June, 15, 1943. He earned a B.S. from Virginia Military Institute. He was Charlottesville's first full-time pediatrician, and cared for four generations of children. He was a founder of Pediatrics Associates and worked as an Associate Professor of Pediatrics at the University of Virginia where he became Chief of the Pediatric Clinic and Director of the blood bank. He also served as a physician at the Blue Ridge School in Dyke and at Woodrow Wilson Rehabilitation Center in Fisherville. He was Chief of Pediatrics at the Martha Jefferson Hospital. He served in the military for 38 years, including active duty in the Army and Air Force. He was awarded the meritorious service medal and the Army commendation medal. He served in many community and professional posts, and was author of numerous publications.
  The inscription on the front cover of the notebook includes "Eastern Laboratory, Gibbstown, N.J." Eastern Laboratory was a research facility developed by DuPont.
- Notebook: Embryology [1939]-40, ADS notebook with drawings, some in color (Box-folder 011-002)
  The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see Box-folder 011-001.
- Student notebook: Bacteriology 1938 November 15-December 13, AD notebook with drawings (Box-folder 011-003)
  The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker when he was an undergraduate student. For more information on Booker see Box-folder 011-001. This is a collection of data sheets.
- Student notebook: Laboratory Assignments for 2nd Term 1940 January 3-March 4, ADS notebook with drawings, some in color (Box-folder 011-004)
  The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see Box-folder 011-001. The assignments were given by Drs. [Robert Bennett] Bean, [Carl] Speidel, and [Wiley Roy] Mason.
- Student notebook: General Medical Studies [I] 1940 January 3-April 15, ADS notebook with drawings, some in color (Box-folder 011-005)
- Student notebook: General Medical Studies [II] 1940 February 13-May 30, ADS notebook with drawings (Box-folder 011-006)
- Student notebook: General Medical Studies [III] 1940 April 17-May 27, ADS notebook with drawings (Box-folder 011-007)
- Student notebook: "Materia Medica, Drug Lists and Laboratory Exercises" Printed in Ann Arbor, Michigan by Edwards Brothers, Inc., 1939. Forward by J[ames] A[lexander] Waddell. 1940 September 16-1941, TDS booklet with A notes and drawings (Box-folder 011-008)
  Professors: James Alexander Waddell (Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica, and Toxicology) and Herbert Silvette (Assistant Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica and Toxicology).
- Student notebook: "Pharmacology; Laboratory Directions and Notes on Pharmacodynamics," Pharmacological Laboratory, University of Virginia, 1938, 7th revision, University Press. 1940 September 16-1941, TDS booklet with A notes and drawings (Box-folder 011-009)
- Student notebook: Anatomy 19[39] September 21, ADS notebook with drawings, some in color (Box-folder 011-010)
- Student notebook: Physiology Laboratory Experiments 1940 September 26 - 1941 February 7, ADS notebook with drawings, some in color (Box-folder 011-011)
  Professors: Sydney William Britton (Professor of Physiology) and Edward Lyman Corey (Assistant Professor of Physiology).
- Student notebook: Physiology 1 and Psychobiology 1940 September 19 - 1941, ADS notebook with drawings (Box-folder 012-001)
  Professors: Physiology: Sydney William Britton (Professor of Physiology) and Edward Lyman Corey (Assistant Professor of Physiology) Psychobiology: Edward Lyman Corey (Assistant Professor of Physiology).
- Student notebook: Pharmacology 1 1940 September 16-December 2, ADS notebook with drawings (Box-folder 012-002)
  Professors: James Alexander Waddell (Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica, and Toxicology), and Herbert Silvette (Assistant Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica, and Toxicology).
- Student notebook: "University of Virginia Physiological Laboratory; An Outline of Experiments in Physiology," Third Edition 1940 September 17, TDS booklet with A notes and drawings (Box-folder 012-003)
- Student notebook: Physiology Laboratory Experiments 1940 October 29-1941 February 28, ADS notebook with drawings, some in color (Box-folder 012-004)
  The experiments were done by J. D. Adams, A. P. Booker, R. Booth, R. Leigh, and F. A. McCue. According to the "University of Virginia Record," John Dean Adams, Armistead Page Booker, Richard Booth, Randolph Leigh, and Frank Armstrong McCue all graduated with an MD degree on March 15, 1943.
- Student notebook: Pharmacology 2 and Pathology 1941 January 3-May 12, ADS notebook (Box-folder 012-005)
  Professors: Pharmacology: James Alexander Waddell (Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica, and Toxicology), and Herbert Silvette (Assistant Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica, and Toxicology); Pathology: James Robert Cash (Walter Reed Professor of Pathology), James Karl Scott (Assistant Professor of Pathology), John Ridley Seal (Instructor of Pathology), Walter Ansell Derrick (Instructor of Pathology), and Lyle Jamesson Hansbrough (Instructor of Pathology).
- Student notebook: Physical Diagnosis and Medicine 1 1941 January 3-February 18, ADS notebook with drawings, some in color (Box-folder 012-006)
  Professors: Eugene Markley Landis (Professor of Internal Medicine), Henry Bearden Mulholland (Professor of Practice of Medicine), James Edwin Wood (Professor of Practice of Medicine), Staige Davis Blackford (Assistant Professor of Medicine), and Oscar Swineford, Jr. (Assistant Professor of Medicine). The lectures are by [Staige Davis] Blackford.
- Student notebook: Physiology 2 and Medicine 2 1941 January 8-March 11, ADS notebook with drawings (Box-folder 012-007)
  Professors: Physiology: Sydney William Britton (Professor of Physiology) and Edward Lyman Corey (Assistant Professor of Physiology); Theory and Practice of Medicine: Eugene Markley Landis (Professor of Internal Medicine), Henry Bearden Mulholland (Professor of Practice of Medicine), James Edwin Wood (Professor of Practice of Medicine), Staige Davis Blackford (Assistant Professor of Medicine), and Oscar Swineford, Jr. (Assistant Professor of Medicine).
- Student notebook: "Toxicology; Supplementary Notes on Toxicology, Chemical Identification, Clinical Symptoms and Signs, Antidotes and Antagonists," Pharmacological Laboratory, University of Virginia, 1941, University Press. 1941 February 10, TDS booklet with A notes (Box-folder 012-008)
- Student notebook: Medicine 3 1941 March 24-December 2, ADS notebook with drawings (Box-folder 012-009)
  Professors: Eugene Markley Landis (Professor of Internal Medicine), Henry Bearden Mulholland (Professor of Practice of Medicine), James Edwin Wood (Professor of Practice of Medicine), Staige Davis Blackford (Assistant Professor of Medicine), and Oscar Swineford, Jr.(Assistant Professor of Medicine); The lecturers include Drs. Wood, E. Wood, and [John Campbell] Hortenstine. Dr. [Henry Bearden] Mulholland held clinic as did Dr. E. Wood.
- Student notebook: Surgery 1 1941 March 24-October 22, ADS notebook with drawings (Box-folder 012-010)
  Professors: Edwin Partridge Lehman (Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), Charles Bruce Morton (Professor of Clinical Surgery and Gynecology), Claude C. Coleman (Clinical Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), Everett Drash (Assistant Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), John Moyer Meredith (Assistant Professor of Neurological Surgery), William Henry Parker (Instructor of Surgery), William Roland Hill (Instructor of Surgery), and Arthur Morton Smith (Instructor of Surgery). The lecturers include Drs. [Edwin Partridge] Lehman, [William Henry] Parker, [William Roland] Hill, and [Charles Bruce] Morton.
- Student notebook: Clinical Diagnosis 1941 March 25-December 12, ADS notebook (Box-folder 012-011)
  Professors: William Edward Bray (Professor of Clinical Pathology and Director of the Clinical Laboratories) and Kenneth Boyd Grim (Instructor of Clinical Pathology).
- Student notebook: Urology and Dermatology 1941 September 22-December 13, ADS notebook (Box-folder 013-001)
  Professors: Urology: Samuel Alexander Vest, Jr. (Associate Professor of Urology), Edgar Wilson Kirby (Assistant Professor of Urology), Howard Harman Curd (Instructor of Urology), James Workman Culbertson (Instructor of Anatomy), and Bruno Barelare, Jr. (Research Fellow in Urology); Dermatology: Dudley Crofford Smith (Professor of Dermatology and Syphilology), Walter Croft Herold (Instructor of Dermatology and Syphilology), and Joseph Leigh Hundley (DuPont Service Fellow in Physiology). The lecturers include Drs.[Samuel Alexander] Vest, [Edgar Wilson] Kirby, and [Bruno] Barelare.
- Student notebook: Obstetrics 1 1941 September 22 - 1942 January 16, ADS notebook (Box-folder 013-002)
  Professors: Tiffany Johns Williams (Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology), John McIntire Nokes (Associate Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology), and William Norman Thornton (Instructor of Obstetrics and Gynecology)The lecturers include Drs. [Tiffany Johns] Williams and [John McIntire] Nokes.
- Student notebook: Pediatrics 1 1941 September 23- 1942 February 24, ADS notebook (Box-folder 013-003)
  Professors: William Wirt Waddell, Jr. (Associate Professor of Pediatrics) and William Herndon Pearson (Instructor of Orthodontia). The lecturers include Drs. [Lawrence Thomas] Royster, [William Wirt] Waddell, and [McLemore] Birdsong.
- Student notebook: Surgery 2 1941 October 27 - 1942 February 10, ADS notebook with drawings (Box-folder 013-004)
  Professors: Edwin Partridge Lehman (Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), Charles Bruce Morton (Professor of Clinical Surgery and Gynecology), Claude C. Coleman (Clinical Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), Everett Drash (Assistant Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), John Moyer Meredith (Assistant Professor of Neurological Surgery), William Henry Parker (Instructor of Surgery), William Roland Hill (Instructor of Surgery), and Arthur Morton Smith (Instructor of Surgery). The lecturers include Drs. [Edwin Partridge] Lehman, [William Gayle] Crutchfield, [Everett Cato] Drash, [Edwin Webster] Shearburn, and [Charles Bruce] Morton.
- Student notebook: Medicine 4 1941 November 26 - 1942 February 25, ADS notebook with drawings (Box-folder 013-005)
  Professors: Eugene Markley Landis (Professor of Internal Medicine), Henry Bearden Mulholland (Professor of Practice of Medicine), James Edwin Wood (Professor of Practice of Medicine), Staige Davis Blackford (Assistant Professor of Medicine), Oscar Swineford, Jr. (Assistant Professor of Medicine), Andrew DeJarnette Hart (Professor of Clinical Medicine and Director of Student Health), John Randolph Tucker Carmichael (Instructor of Medicine), and John Lippincott Guerrant (DuPont Service Fellow in Internal Medicine). The lecturers include Drs. E. Wood. [Byrd Stuart] Leavell, [William Maryon] Moir, and [Henry Bearden] Mulholland.
- Student notebook: Orthopedics N. & P. 1 1942 January 5-November 3, ADS notebook with drawings (Box-folder 013-006)
  Professors: Orthopedics: Robert Vivian Funsten (Professor of Orthopedics), Charles Ames Frankel (Instructor of Orthopedic Surgery), Richard Taylor Ergenbright (Instructor of Orthopedics), Lloyd Delbert Fisher (Instructor of Orthopedic Surgery), and Dr. Harris; Neurology and Psychiatrics: David Cole Wilson (Professor of Psychiatry and Neurology). The lecturers include Dr. [David Cole] Wilson.
- Student notebook: Obstetrics 2 and Sanitation, Statistics, and Epidemiology 1942 January 16 - 1943 February 26, ADS notebook (Box-folder 013-007)
  The lecturers include Drs. [John McIntire] Nokes and [Thomas Shepherd] Englar.
- Student notebook: Pediatrics 2 and Preventive Mediciine and Epidemiology 1942 February 26-September 3, ADS notebook (Box-folder 013-008)